Guide to the Planned Parenthood of Houston & Southeast Tex. Records
University of Houston Libraries
Planned Parenthood of Houston & Southeast Tex. Records
1936-2004
02/2010-007
Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas
17.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection is comprised of 12 boxes and 17 linear feet and documents the evolution of the Maternal Health Center of Houston into the Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas branch. Material in the collection is dated from 1936 until 2004. The collection contains historical information about the origins of the Planned Parenthood of Southeast Texas and the Maternal Health Center as well as the national birth control movement and Planned Parenthood Federation.
Historical Note:
Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, now known as Planned Parenthood Gulf Coast, opened its doors in February of 1936 under the name Maternal Health Center of Houston. Under the direction of Agnese Carter Nelms and her brother-in-law Dr. Judson L. Taylor the Maternal Health Center was dedicated to helping poor and indigent women in Houston receive health care and an education on family planning. The original purpose of the Maternal Health Center was stated as, “to establish and maintain a free medical clinic for the use and benefit of mothers and prospective mothers of the City of Houston and to furnish mothers and prospective mothers of Houston free medical advice on maternal health” (Anderson 8). Eventually, through Agnese Nelms’ tireless work and advocacy of family planning and the birth control movement, the Maternal Health Center gained the support of many of Houston’s prominent community leaders. The first board of directors included many of Houston’s elite, and the wealthiest and most successful businessmen and their wives, such as Mrs. Will Clayton, Maurice and Susan McAshan, the Rev. J. Elmer Ferguson, Rosalie Farish, and Mrs. John Bullington (11 Anderson).
Birth control and family planning remained controversial for the next several decades and the Maternal Health Center volunteers kept the clinic alive through word of mouth and door-to-door grass roots campaigning. They remained loosely affiliated with the American Birth Control League, which eventually became the Planned Parenthood Federation of America in 1942. This affiliation with the American Birth Control League would lead, ultimately, to the incorporation of the Maternal Health Center with the Planned Parenthood Federation of America.
In the late 1940s the Maternal Health Center was renamed to the Planned Parenthood Center of Houston, and after the legalization of birth control with the Supreme Court’s 1965 Griswold vs. Connecticut decision the Center grew to include many satellite clinics and thus renamed itself to Planned Parenthood of Houston.
The institution continued to grow, adding vasectomy clinics, more women’s clinics and focusing on public outreach and education, until it merged with several other Planned Parenthoods in Texas to become, in 1978, Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. By 1984 the organization was seeing as many as 60,000 patients a year (5 Molan).
In 2010 Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas was renamed again to the Planned Parenthood Gulf Coast as it absorbed clinics in Louisiana and other areas of Texas. It continues to grow, expanding its public education and outreach services, expanding sex education access in schools and offering low cost health care, contraception and counseling and abortions. Its slogan remains “every child a wanted child.”
References:
Anderson, Maria Helen. Private choices vs. public voices: The history of Planned Parenthood in Houston. Diss. Rice University, 1998. Dissertations & Theses: Full Text, ProQuest. Web. 2 Dec. 2010.
Molan, Michelle R. Proud of our past planning the future: 50 years of Planned Parenthood. Houston, TX: Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, 1986.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Planned Parenthood Federation of America; Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas
Genre/Form of Material:
Audiotapes; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Newspapers; Pamphlets; Periodicals; Photographs; Typescripts
Personal Name:
Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966
Topical Term:
Birth control; Birth control clinics -- Texas -- Bryan; Birth control clinics -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of 12 boxes and 17 linear feet and documents the evolution of the Maternal Health Center of Houston into the Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas branch. Material in the collection is dated from 1936 until 2004. The collection contains historical information about the origins of the Planned Parenthood of Southeast Texas and the Maternal Health Center as well as the national birth control movement and Planned Parenthood Federation. The collection features an extensive series of recorded and transcribed oral interviews documenting the memories of staff and patients of Planned Parenthood of Southeast Texas, as well as an unpublished written history of the organization called Sixty Years of choice. In addition, there is a large series of dated photographs featuring staff of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, and chronicling their fundraisers, galas and other events. A large part of the Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas’s work involves community education and outreach thus a large series contains the publications and pamphlets used for these purposes, as well as the newspaper articles and clippings from Houston and national periodicals featuring topics of interest to the organization. Smaller series feature the financial history of the organization dating back to the Maternal Health Center, correspondence from the organization, and publications from organizations affiliated with Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas.
Detailed List of Contents
- Origins and history of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, id103677
  Scope and Contents
  This series is contained in 1 box and is comprised of 33 folders. It has items dating from 1935 until 2004 and contains documents related to the history of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. Of particular interest are documents related to Margaret Sanger, including an early copy of her controversial pamphlet on contraception called Family Limitation. Additionally the annual reports of Planned Parenthood through the years are included, as well as the unpublished history Sixty years of choice which chronicles the growth of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas from its origins as the underfunded volunteer organization the Maternal Health Center of Houston.
  - Chronology of the birth control movement publication, id104023 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birth control movement publications, 1935 – 1968; id104024 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Margaret Sanger publications and information, including a copy of Family Limitation, id104025 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maternal Health Center of Houston and Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas origins, id104026 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Planned Parenthood beginnings, state histories, id104027 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Planned Parenthood beginnings, state histories – copy, id104028 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas – 50th Anniversary, id104029 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Dear Planned Parenthood” tribute, id104030 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Schwanecke vs Vaseem, et. all (class action law suit against Planned Parenthood), id104031 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas – board of directors reports, minutes, etc., 1968 – 2001; id104032 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas annual reports, 1975 – 1979; id104033 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas annual reports, 1980 – 1982, 1984 – 1987; id104034 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas annual reports, 2001, 2003-2004; id104035 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas newsletters, 1973 – 1979; id104036 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas newsletters, 1983-1990; id104037 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Plan it” newsletter of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, 2004; id104038 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas Gazette – Staff newsletter, Sept 1995; id104039 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Related errata, id104040 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Typescript, pp 1-109, id104041 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Typescript, pp 110 – 232, id104042 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Early draft with editing notes and marginalia, id104043 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1930s chapter, draft, editing notes on whole book, id104044 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1940s chapter, draft, id104045 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1950s chapter, draft, id104046 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1960s chapter, draft, id104047 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1970 – 1976, draft, id104048 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1977 – 1987 draft, id104049 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – 1988 – 1997 draft, id104050 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Draft, pp 1- 78, id104051 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Draft, pp 80 – 145, id104052 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Draft, pp 146 – 232, id104053 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Draft, small print, pp 1 – 107, id104054 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - “Sixty years of choice” – Draft, small print, pp 108 - end, id104055 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Oral History Interviews, id103678
  This series is contained in one box and has 28 folders, and is organized alphabetically and topically. The interviews were conducted between 1995 and 1997. It features the transcripts and original recordings of the oral history interviews conducted by Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. The oral history interviews were conducted to gain the personal perspective of Houston citizens impacted by Planned Parenthood on its effect on their lives. It includes the data sheets for the interviewees.
  - Cassette recordings of oral history interviews, id104085 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Historical interviews – floppy disk, id104086 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Transcripts – related correspondence, id104087 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Transcript – Brown, Kathleen, 6 Jul, 1995; id104088 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Transcript – Cohen, Meryl, 23 Jun, 1995; id104089 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Transcript – Dallred, Carol, 9 Aug, 1995; id104090 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Transcript – Durkin, Peter, 1 Mar, 1995; id104091 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Transcript – Edwards, Jerry (interview 2), 7 Mar, 1996; id104092 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcript – Elias, Judy, 16 Aug, 1995; id104093 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Transcript – Ely, Jane, 22 May, 19956; id104094 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Transcript –Emmert, Steven, 18 Jul, 1995; id104095 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Transcript -- Fred, Ruth, 19 Jun, 1996; id104096 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Transcript – Grant, Cynthia, 13 Jul, 1995; id104097 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Transcript – Hughes, Mary (N.D.), id104098 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Transcript -- Jarvis, Christine, 23 Jun, 1995; id104099 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Transcript – Kelsey, Wendy, 23 Apr, 1996; id104100 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transcript -- Linton, Melaney A., 12 Jul, 1995; id104101 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Transcript -- Lopez, Kimberly, 9 Aug, 1995; id104102 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Transcript – McGill, Laurie, 18 Jul, 1995; id104103 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Transcript – Mumford, David, 4 Sept, 1996; id104104 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Transcript -- Orton, Hanni, 8 May, 1996; id104105 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Transcript – Peterkin, Nancy, 9 Jul, 1996; id104106 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Transcript -- Rae, Jane, 9 May, 1996; id104107 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Transcript – Straus, Carol, 8 May, 1996; id104108 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Transcript – Tekle, Marie, 25 Jul, 1995; id104109 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Transcript – VanKerrebrook, Phyllis, 8 Jun, 1995; id104110 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Transcript – White, Rebecca, 13 Jul, 1995; id104111 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Transcript – Wilson, Isabel Brown, 14 Feb, 1997; id104112 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, id103679
  This series is contained in 1 box and has 7 folders, arranged chronologically. The contained correspondence is dated from 1947 until 2007. It contains correspondence to and from representatives of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, as well as correspondence with affiliated organizations and other Houston individuals involved with the organization.
  - Undated, id104114 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1947, id104115 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1966 – 1976, id104116 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1977 – 1979, id104117 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1980 – 1983, id104118 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1984 – 1992, id104119 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1994 – 2007, id104120 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Photographic Material, id103680
  This series is contained in 1 box and has 47 folders, arranged chronologically and ranging from 1977 - 1996. Some of the photos are identified by person or event but the majority is unidentified, although arranged by year. The photographic files chronicle events of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas through the years, including their galas, other fundraisers, and political events.
  - before 1977, id104122 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1979, id104123 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1980, id104124 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1981, id104125 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1982, id104126 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1983, id104127 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1984, id104128 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 1985, id104129 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 1986, id104130 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Diane’s goodbye, 1986; id104131 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Press conference, Lufkin open house, 1986; id104132 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Sarah Weddington photos, 1986; id104133 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - 50th Planned Parenthood Gala, 1986; id104134 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - 1988, id104135 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - 1st Roe vs. Wade luncheon, 1988; id104136 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Washington March, 1988/1989; id104137 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - 1989, id104138 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1989, id104139 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Pro-choice rally, Austin, TX., 11-12-1989; id104140 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Pro-choice rally, Austin, TX, 11-12-1989; id104141 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - 1990, id104142 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Linda Ellerbee Luncheon, 1990; id104143 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Economic Summit protesters and party, 1990; id104144 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - 1991, id104145 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Auction, 1991; id104146 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Gala, 1991; id104147 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1992, id104148 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - post – GOP volunteer party, 1992; id104149 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Gala – Houston Museum of Natural Science, 1992; id104150 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Breakfast reunion (Aug), 1993; id104151 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Race for the cure (Oct), 1993; id104152 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - New Planned Parenthood name, 1993; id104153 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Joshua Graff photos, 1993; id104154 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Art Car parade, 1994; id104155 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Preceptor lunch, 1994; id104156 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Unused annual report negatives, 1994; id104157 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Holiday pictures, 1994; id104158 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Board & seniority recognition, 1995; id104159 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Negatives, protester Mary Shelvin going away, 1995; id104160 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Annual meeting, 1995; id104161 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Volunteer recognition party at Chapultepec, 1995; id104162 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous volunteers, 1995; id104163 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - 1996, id104164 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Planned Parenthood March for Choice and health fair, 1996; id104165 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Staff photos, unknown; id104166 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Unknown events, id104167 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Unknown events, id104168 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Financial, taxation and legal documents, id103681
  This series is contained in one box and has 15 folders and ranges from 1938 - 1985. It contains the financial and legal documents of both the Maternal Health Center and the various incarnations of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. Of particular interest are the loans and the IRS records for Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas to receive its tax-exempt status. Contained, as well, is budgeting information for the various Planned Parenthood activities throughout its years.
  - Maternal Health Center financial reports, 1938 – 1941; id104170 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports, 1948 – 1950; id104171 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports, 1960, 1962 – 1966; id104172 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports, 1967, 1969 – 1972; id104173 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports, 1973-1975; id104174 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports and tax documents, 1976; id104175 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial reports and tax documents, 1977 – 1978; id104176 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial records, 1982; id104177 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial records, 1983; id104178 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial records, 1984; id104179 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston financial records, 1985; id104180 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas tax documents, exempt status, id104181 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas tax documents, id104182 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas deed, legal documents and related correspondence, id104183 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas titles, loans and other legal documents, id104184 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Publications, slides and training information, id103682
  This series is contained in 1 box and is comprised of 20 folders. It contains items dating from 1974 until 1996 and many undated items. This series contains pamphlets, flyers and educational information published by Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. In addition it contains documents and slides used to train the volunteers and employees of Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas.
  - Volunteer information booklet, id104186 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Volunteers and staff information, 1974-1975; id104187 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Volunteers and staff, 1978-1981; id104188 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Volunteers and staff, 1982 - 1983; id104189 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Volunteers and staff, 1984 – 1985; id104190 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Volunteer newsletters, 1985 – 1996; id104191 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mary Elizabeth Hudson Resource Center manual, id104192 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Planned Parenthood informational and training slides, id104193 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - RNC Slides, 1992; id104194 (Box 4, Folder 24-26)
  - Planned Parenthood presentations, speeches and hotline, id104197 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Vasectomy information, id104198 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Community outreach pamphlets/publications, id104199 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Demographics pamphlets/publications, id104201 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Political pamphlets/publications, id104202 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Educational pamphlets/publications, id104203 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Medical studies and trials, id103683
  This short series is contained in 1 box and spans 2 folders with dates ranging from 1990 - 1997. Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas was involved in several clinical trials for contraception and abortion medications in the United States. The Mifepristone study, also known as RU486, is of particular interest. The series contains information on the studies, press-release information and public outreach information as well as medical results.
  - Methotrexate study, 1996; id104205 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Mifepristone (RU486) Study, 1994; id104206 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Media and donor outreach and related newspaper clippings and advertisements, id103684
  This series is contained in 1 box and has 20 folders, spanning from 1985 to 1997. It contains documents related to Planned Parenthood’s extensive media outreach program and its fundraising activities. Contained are records of the names of reporters, solicited newspaper articles, advertisements and other public outreach activities of the organization.
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, 1985 – 1988; id104208 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, 1990 - 1991; id104209 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Media inquiry check list, press releases, Oct 1991 – Dec 1992; id104210 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, 1992; id104211 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jan – Jun 1993; id104212 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jul – Dec 1993; id104213 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jan – Jun 1994; id104214 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jul – Oct 1994; id104215 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Press releases, 1994; id104216 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Press releases, 1995; id104217 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, 1995; id104218 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Press releases, 1996; id104219 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, 1996; id104220 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jan – Jun 1997; id104221 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Media and donor outreach, press releases, Jul – Dec 1997; id104222 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Press Releases, 1997; id104223 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Media and donor outreach duplicates, 1986 – 1994; id104224 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Press releases, duplicates, 1986 – 1994; id104225 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Donors and fundraising, id104226 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas advertisements, id104227 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Affiliated Organizations with Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas, id103685
  This series is contained in 3 boxes and contains 46 folders, with items dating from 1945 until 2002. This series features documents and publications from organizations affiliated with Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. A particularly large set of documents is related to the Bryan Planned Parenthood branch, a sister organization to Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas. Another particularly large group of documents are related to the various population control organizations affiliated with Planned Parenthood of Houston and Southeast Texas that were endorsing family planning as an environmental, health and social concern necessary for human existence on the planet.
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America publications, 1945 – 1974; id109148 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America annual reports (inc), 1972 – 1989; id109149 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Planned Parenthood memorandums and reports, 1970 – 1972; id109150 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Planned Parenthood Federation of America “Insider” newsletter, 1988 - 1989; id109151 (Box 5, Folder 24)